<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copie of a letter, sent by and English gentleman out of France to a friend of his in England, concerning the great victorie which the French king obtained against the duke de Maine, and the Romish rebels in his kingdome, vpon the fourth daie of March last past. 1589. Wherein is particularly expressed the names of sundrie noblemen, with the number of horsemen &amp; footmen which were drowned, slaine, hurt, and taken prisoners in the sayd battaile.</title>
            <author>T. B., English gentleman out of France.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00553</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1069.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117960</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853169</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853169</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18538</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00553)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18538)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 506:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copie of a letter, sent by and English gentleman out of France to a friend of his in England, concerning the great victorie which the French king obtained against the duke de Maine, and the Romish rebels in his kingdome, vpon the fourth daie of March last past. 1589. Wherein is particularly expressed the names of sundrie noblemen, with the number of horsemen &amp; footmen which were drowned, slaine, hurt, and taken prisoners in the sayd battaile.</title>
                  <author>T. B., English gentleman out of France.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Wolfe] for William Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 10411.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 10411 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18538:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18538:1"/>
            <p>THE Copie of a Letter, <hi>ſent by an Engliſh Gentleman out of France,</hi> to a friend of his in <hi>England,</hi> concerning the great victorie which the French King obtained againſt the Duke de Maine, and the Romiſh rebels in his Kingdome, vpon the fourth daie of March laſt paſt. 1589.</p>
            <p>Wherein is particularly expreſſed the names of ſundrie noble men, with the number of horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men &amp; footmen which were drowned, ſlaine, hurt, and taken priſoners in the ſayd Battaile.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed for William Wright.</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:18538:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18538:2"/>
            <head>THE COPY OF A LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſent by an Engliſh Gentleman forth of France, to a friend of his in England, concerning the great victorie which the French King obtained againſt the Duke de Maine, and the Romiſh rebels in his Kingdom, vpon the fourth daie of March laſt paſt. 1589.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y good Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>the manifold curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies by me ſundrie waies receiued at your handes, makes me not to bee vnmindfull of you, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that I finde you not ſlack to ſignifie vnto me from time to time, ſuch newes as Englande affordeth, I thought it good there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to make requitall of ſome part of your paines by certefieng vnto you, the moſt happie and ioyfull newes now generally knowne for truth throughout the whole Realme of France. The circumſtance whereof at large deſerueth a ſtately ſtile, a large volume, and to be regeſtred in letters of golde, ſuch and ſo rare an euent the Almightie hath brought to paſſe, to the great comfort of the Kings Maieſtie (whome God preſerue and proſper) to the great benefit and ioy of all his dutifull and loiall ſubiects,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18538:3"/> which now by the prouidence of God doth daily increaſe: and to the great diſcouragement of all the enemies to Chriſtian religion, which to recorde or diſcourſe by circumſtance at large, I leaue to thoſe of deepe ſkill and ſufficient learning, to enroll amongſt the noble actes of the moſt renowmed and valianteſt of our age. Onely to you I doe heare ſend a briefe particular of his Maieſties good fortune happened vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the fourth daie of March laſt paſt. A matter containing ſo great certaintie, and yet ſo incredible (for that the enemie was three to one in the field) as doth make men wonder at the ſame, and hardly beleeue it. But there is nothing vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to compaſſe or obtaine where God is the guide, nor nothing proſpereth or preuaileth where Gods aſſiſtance wanteth, as I could proue by many examples: What pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er can preuaile to fight againſt Gods truth, then the which, nothing is of more force, as appeareth by that which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth.</p>
            <p>It is not vnknowen vnto you by our laſt conference to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at your lodging, where conferring with a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that had trauelled into <hi>France</hi> vpon the preſent ſtate of that Countrie, he declared that then the ſtate was verie dangerous, and the land was diuided into three ſeuerall fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which is ſince altered into two, the one very lawfull, being vnder the conduct of the lawfull King: the other a greater and of more danger, for that they are Traitours to their King, ſtirred vp in the life time of the bloudthirſtie Duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> who became the onely capitall enemie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſtian religion, and the profeſſours thereof throughout all Chriſtendom, as appeared by the great mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, maſſacre and ſlaughter of many thouſandes by him and his aſſociates inflicted and committed at <hi>Paris</hi> in his life time vppon the profeſſours of the reformed Religion: who as he liued, died: hee ſlaughtered innocentes, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in their bloud, till other requited him with the lyke death.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18538:3"/>
            <p>After which, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the right of the <hi>Guize</hi> for the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſion to the Crowue and Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> (who had no right at all thereunto) the Duke <hi>de Maine,</hi> a man ſupported and maintained by the Pope and all the ſworne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the Goſpell, was found by them the fitteſt cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion in that Countrie, to rebell and riſe vp in armes againſt the King, being no loyall ſubiect, but a rebellious Traitor to the Crowne of <hi>France.</hi> For after the death of the French King, he tooke vpon him the title of the King, and in moſt diſloiall ſorte repugned againſt the lawfull and Chriſtian King <hi>Henrie</hi> of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> now ſince proclaimed and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the lawfull ſucceſſour to the crowne and kingdome. All which notwithſtanding the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> reſiſted his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, by meanes of the great forces ſent him by the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh enemies, and to the entent to diſplace and depoſe him vnlawfully, hath with his power ſundry times ſet vpon the Kinges Forces, and taken his chiefeſt Cities and walled Townes, and doeth withhold them vnlawfully from the King, contrarie to the dutie of a naturall ſubiect, ſo that after many late battailes and ſkirmiſhes, one onely battayle was fought vpon the fourth day of March aforeſaid, where the enemy was thirtie thouſand ſtrong in the field, the King not hauing aboue ten thouſand in all: beſides there was newly come foorth of the low Countries fiue thouſand foote-men, and fouretéene Coronets of Horſe-men, all which were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſlaine, and put to the ſword, twelue hundred of the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were drowned, and the reſt taken by the Kings Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Before the Battaile began, for that the enemy was more then thrée to one, (the King then being in ſuch a place where he muſt fight it out or die) tooke courage and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Souldiers, ſhewing them that the cauſe was a iuſt cauſe, and did repoſe therefore his truſt in God onely: in whoſe quarrell he fought, and he would defend him from the furie of his enemies, as he had ſundry times before deliuered him from the like dangers: willing his Souldiers not to be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18538:4"/> daunted with the multitude which came towards them: for ſaid hee, I will bee the foremoſt, and will ſpende my deareſt blood before any of you ſhall periſh: which wordes did ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Souldiers that they fell to it, and got to a firme and faire péece of ground, being of great compaſſe, and kept that ground ſtill and woulde not giue backe, whereby the enemy might haue any aduantage: who for want of ground to fight and ſtirre themſelues, the multitude peſtered one an other, ſo that their great multitude and want of roome was the greateſt cauſe of their ouerthrowe, which the King perceiued, and encouraged his men to fight, who verie fiercely laide vpon the enemy, and broke their ranke and diſordered their Battaile, whereupon the King to the great diſcomfort of the enemy, ſtept to the Standard bearer of the enemies Army, hee tooke away the Standard with his owne handes, and ſlue the bearer thereof, which did ſo encourage his Souldiers, that they fell to it ſo fiercely, as that they conſtrained the Duke to flie, when hee ſawe his owne brother ſlaine before his face, and was almoſt taken in the flight. The King had the enemy in the Chaſe ſeuen Leagues, wherein there were a thouſand men of name and account taken priſoners. The Counti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Egmont</hi> was ſlaine in this Battaile, and <hi>Mounſieur de la Mount,</hi> was taken priſoner. Foure hundreth golden Chaines and more, were found in the rifling of the Waggins, and ſeuen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Choſts of pillage taken by the King, beſides the Dukes Caſket, wherein was encloſed his chiefeſt Letters of priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. All the Switzers haue ſurrendred themſelues to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection and obedience of the King: And the enemies chiefeſt field Péeces were taken.</p>
            <p>Thus was the enemies Forces, greatly weakened and ſcattered, ſo that it is very likely <hi>Parris</hi> and the chiefeſt Townes and places now repugnant againſt him, will not long hold out, but yeeld themſelues ſpéedily to his Maieſties mercy. God be bleſſed, he hath wonderfully preſerued this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18538:4"/> godly and chriſtian Prince from dan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, being ſtill the moſt forwardeſt in the fight, and chaſed them almoſt eight houres togither. The God of heauen proſper him and all the fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the Chriſtian Religion, that they may beate downe ſuch as ſeeke the confuſion thereof, and giue his enemies grace to ſee their owne folly and leaue their blind ignorance, that either their conuerſion may be ſpeedily ſeene, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of their former follies, or els their deſtruction pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently come vpon them, which God grant ſpeedily, for his mercies ſake, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>This ſixt of March.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your louing friend, T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Another letter <date>the 6. of March.</date>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He</hi> kings Maieſty ſent for the gouernour and the Nobility, and for prouiſion of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to giue battail to the Duke <hi>de Maine.</hi> The Duke preſſed vpon the King, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Wallons, being foure thouſand foote and one thouſand horſe. The gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the way met with two companyes of footemen and diſcomforted them: and tooke theyr Captayn priſoners to <hi>Font delarche,</hi> vpon his arriuall the King gaue battayl to the Duke, and put him to the worſe. The Duke fled, moſt of the Burgonians were ſlaine, his ordinance loſt: and foure thouſand Switzers were receaued to mercy and the ſeruice of the King. <hi>Mounſier Mountpenſier</hi> did very valiantly, he was a little hurt in the head, the <hi>Cownt Egmont</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductor of the Spaniards and Wallons, was ſlain and their ſtandard taken: the King was forced to the battayl by the Duke, and therefore could not refuſe it. The Duke was moued thereto by the Popes legat, through diſcontemnent grown among them of <hi>Paris,</hi> by reaſon of the charges they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18538:5"/> had <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>e put vnto by the Duke and no ſer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>e done, and therefore grew to a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>tation, whether better to yéeld to the King, or to thoſe of the league: Sundry of the chéefeſt murmured at the motion of Spayn, which being obſerued, were the night folowing apprehended and committed to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. This deuiſion was the cheefe cauſe that the leggat made <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>e of battel, whereas the Duke was obedient. To conclude, the enemy was thrée to one, and yet God bee pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed few on the Kings ſide were hurt and the moſt part of the enemies were drownd, ſlayn, hurt, and taken priſoners in the battell.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The names of ſuch chiefe perſons as were ſlain and hurt on the enemies ſide.</head>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <head>Slaine.</head>
                     <item>The County <hi>Egmont</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Duke <hi>Brunswicke</hi> general of the Reiſters.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18538:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
